[Music]
Hello, welcome everyone. It is May 2nd,
2025. We're in active guest stream
105.1 with PA Deio discussing systemic
deviation from systemic failures to
systemic aberration.
We will first be playing a pre-recorded
lecture and then follow that with a
discussion with PA and Jeff Schelman
here. So, looking forward to everyone's
comments in the live chat. And here we
go with the pre-recorded
video. Daniel at the active inference
institute and friends. Daniel and
friends uh to
um talk a little bit about my work and
um they picked a topic from one of my
papers called systemic deviation and
I've taken the opportunity to uh remind
myself uh how does this systemic
deviation thing I wrote
about some time ago applies today. So um
in the process of reviewing the paper
which I wrote few years ago um on the
topic actually I have updated it and
realized that it's not only
um relevant it also has this concept of
systemication has got like profound
implication in
uh helping us to understand a number of
things which are going on today. And so
the new title for the topic systemic
deviation is from systemic failures to
systemic
aberration. It's a huge topic. So thank
you so much for bearing with me and uh
the it's about 50 slides and I will try
to go through them as quickly as
possible. But um because I don't like to
hurry too much and speaking too fast
although I've got so much to say in such
a little time. I think I
recommend that people listening to the
talk will uh play replay it at 1.5 speed
so that all this um pausing that I do
while I'm reading um doesn't slow you
down. So systemic deviation refers to a
behavioral and functional shift of a
system from its intended
purpose and is particularly relevant in
the context of intelligent and
autonomous system.
So what is systemic mediation? It's a
theory, a lens, a paradigm, a
framework. Just could be anything that
you want it to be in a way. Um and uh
that's let's take it as a book concept
at the
moment. So roughly this is going to be
the content of the talk. introduction,
background,
examples, mitigation
measures,
systems, and this table of contents in
fact was written up before I finalize
the slide. So, we may deviate a little
bit. This is just indicative.
And about me,
um I'm a teacher, writer, traveler, um
interested in nature, complimentary
health systems, metaphysics, and I'm
asking myself the big questions all the
time. And eventually it wasn't easy for
me to focus on an academic uh life
because um of my diversity of interest.
But then luckily in this recent years,
it's okay to be multi-disiplinary.
So uh my academic focus in the last say
10 years after my PhD has been
information technology intelligence
systems knowledge representation. I've
got lots to say about this topic
interfaces neuroscience uh neurom
modulation meta science. So basically we
are trying to follow and uh gather
insights into every little topic that
matters today.
So
um there was a paper called systemic
deviation the evil in the machine which
can be found online easily and it was
published by the uh international
society
for systems. It was a presentation I did
at some conference then
um and it was a little bit like
scratching the surface. So this is a
great opportunity. Thank you Daniel and
Hector who said let's talk about this
topic again because it's really good to
go back to it and see what does this
tell us about what we arrest really then
the other if you want to know a little
bit more you go into psychological abuse
and you say why oh I'll tell you later
but basically there is an
[Applause]
interesting an interesting uh direction
for the systemic deviation into the
cognition and psychology ology of how
this what this does to people. So uh
thanks to another opportunity unrelated
a couple of years ago uh into looking at
the the psychiatry rather it was but you
know like there was something that
system deviation does to people and so
if you may be interested in that you can
just click and um eventually what we're
getting at is systemic abuse
institutional abuse is something
that systemic litigation can help us to
figure out what's happening. So why why
psychological abuse uh and systemic
abuse is because technical systems and
social technical systems can be designed
to perpetrate systemic abuse. Now you
never thought about that when when you
when you write down when you sit down to
write a system or design a system or
implement a system you don't think what
is it going to do to people um you think
does it do what it's supposed to do in
terms of
functionality you think of the
engineering side but then
ultimately now that we are becoming so
dependent on systems and we interact
with systems at every level every day um
they can be quite invasive systems as we
as we are realizing izing with AI
pervasive but also invasive. So systemic
mediation uh can be turned into abuse
when it's turned into abuse can lead to
psychological impairment. So ultimately
this is why uh I am uh matching the
systemic abuse systemic deviation which
is more like a
technical a technical thing in relation
to how systems cannot do what they're
supposed to do but it becomes relevant
to to social technical
systems more importantly and more
worryingly that we cannot see and cannot
we like users or individuals or
stakeholders cannot see and cannot
understand. If we cannot understand
division uh we may not realize what is
happening uh between um
the you know we cannot it's like it's
important to understand that uh systemic
deviation actually
uh can have some consequences on
cognition and psychology.
still in the title as you can see the
title I put the word systemic aberation
it wasn't there in the original work but
now that I've had a chance to see how
things are progressing I definitely say
we systemic deviation will lead to
systemic
aberration what is what we mean
aberration so actually in science it's
it comes from a term coming from optics
the field of optics and it's described
as the failure of rays to converge at
one focus because of a defect in the
lens of the mirror. We could say that a
systemic deviation is that defect, you
know, if we use the optics analog
analogy, systemic deviation is like some
kind of defects that prevents us from
seeing uh getting a focus on on
whatever. So, but also of course there
is a stenic aberration is a term used in
biology and more generically speaking is
a departure from what is normal, usual
or respected in a negative sense. So, um
and we're seeing now how systemic
deviation can lead to systemic
aberration. It it's a it's not a ch it's
not a mistake is designed. uh I can see
that I've started seeing that and this
is the main message that this
presentation gives. Um I figured it out
and I'm sharing it with uh people who
are interested in uh looking into this
possibility that we are all
um conditioned by systemic deviation one
way or another. So before moving on
focusing on systemic deviation
um with a bit more attention I'd like to
share this um table which was in fact
made by Gemini to which I'm grateful um
that is
um comparing institutional abuse with
systemic
abuse. So is this systemic mediation
leading to some kind of aberration and
abuse abuse
is also not particularly well
understood. It does we don't understand
how it happens and what it does to
people.
But in my work I've had the chance to
distinguish between the two and um
Gemini did a wonderful job at
distinguishing the two
using categories level source of arm
scope focus perpetrator. I don't know if
I necessarily agree with this
distinctions here, but it's very helpful
to start as a starting point. So, uh,
institutional abuse, uh, the level is
micromeso or macro in systemic abuse,
source of harm, um, failures within an
in institutional abuse. The source of
harm is failures within an institution
and systemic abuse is broader societal
structures. And here I would put social
technical systems as well. The sword of
arm is the poor system. This one
scope institutional abuse is
localized. Systemic abuse is widespread.
Focus
um occurring inside the institution
versus generated by the way the system
is structured. This is where our
systemic deviation comes in really very
clearly. Perpetrator individuals versus
system structure. So I think we're
aiming we're looking at this but then
very often the relationship. So when the
institution is a system or is operates
through a system then the two overlap
clearly.
So the purpose of the present of this
presentation is to identify and map
issues critical to survival ultimately
uh to uh to health or healthy survival
building the foundations of the paper
which I mentioned earlier.
Um to see how this notion of systemic
deviation which identified in 2016 has
evolved and how does it apply today we
identify further examples. So in this
paper I gave few examples but things
have moved on and we have lot more
examples today and to increase situation
awareness analysis and find possible
solutions and find some synergy with
others who uh resonate with this topic.
So systemic failure in the title
somewhere there is also systemic
failure. So systemic deviation will lead
to systemic failure is a failure that
happen in a deterministic non-random
predictable fashion. This is taken from
some uh dictionary or definition a
Google definition. Predictable fashion
failure that happens in a deterministic
nonrandom predictable fashion from a
certain
cause which can only be eliminated by
modification of the design of the
manufacturing process of the process.
Let's forget manufacturing here
operational procedures documentation or
other relevant factors. So it's very
important to understand that very often
when things go wrong is that because
they were resigned like
that. Um systemic deviation can be a
contributing factor. I'm not saying that
every case is like that but and it
results in a system not fulfilling its
declare purpose or fulfilling opposing
purpose which is you know where the
aberration takes place.
So to have a system that doesn't not fit
for purpose is kind of common, but to
have a system that's not exactly the
system designed to be is is the blatant
aberration. Um example of systemic
failures. Okay, in the paper these
examples are brought up. I'm not going
to spend too much time on it because you
can read the paper, but
basically hospitals that kill patients
by
accident. Very
common corruption in law enforcement
agency. Oo, very common. States and
governments run by
insiders. I'm sure you know all about
that. Democracies that are governed by
run by elites. You can't see that, but
you know it's there. Media disseminating
this
information. I'm sure you've heard that
one. Seemingly progressive movements
that are actually set up to stir and
drive repression.
Uh this is very interesting when you see
that people especially in industry you
say oh I didn't realize it for a long
time you know as a young girl I was
going into trade learning about trade
and market
and then I realized that the consumer
association is actually driven by the
industry or setup is like these are
these are
uh this you know set up to deceive and
to distort the consumer's view but uh we
You need to evolve the thinking and the
awareness to be able to see that. I
didn't see that for a long time. And
when I
did, it did have a consequence on my
ability to function as an you know my
psychology really on how do I perceive
the
world. Open data initiative masterminded
by secretive individuals. I'm sure. I
mean, I've seen that, especially the
open
sides. Ships designed to
sink. I don't think that was the case
with Titanic, but I don't think it was
designed to sink, but it was definitely
a design issue that sack it. And how
come how come something like the
Titanic was not the flaws, the Titanic
design was not
spotted, you know? I'm not sure. I don't
think it was intentional in that case,
but it was a terri terrible accident.
And probably there are more in the
history.
Um, and transparency initiatives
designed and led by people and
organizations who want to make
transparent models fit. That's very
similar to the open data. So they're
saying, "Oh, we want transparency." And
then they put the label transparency on
the initiative, but actually the
initiative itself is completely opaque.
And this uh conflict between the label
and what the thing that the system does
is cause of disorientation in anyone
who's looking at it. So when we talk
about abuse, we're looking at cause of
harm, psychological and emotional
manipulation, systemic
unfairness. Systemic unfairness is
causing shifts in collective
consciousness and possibly even genetic
mutation. This is will be interesting to
investigate. Many levels technical, so
technical,
organizational, societal misinformation,
family, workplace, very complex
multistakeholder
scenarios. So
abuse is not understood. There is a lack
of societal awareness of the abuse
problem. It's almost because as I say in
the presentation about psychological
abuse is historical. So schools,
families, parents, children
relationship,
uh religion, institutions, they're all
designed
to inflict some kind of abuse. So where
abuse is perceived as good for you like
discipline very often abuse discipline
or good discipline is confused with
abuse and therefore we are unable to
distinguish this is abuse because we
think that's the way things are and
that's the way things work but um I
think we are trying to make progress
towards a more compassionate um and
mindful society therefore we are
becoming increasingly aware but at large
in uh institutions it still ignores what
abuse consists of and the consequences
of harm are uh immense. So what are we
looking at again? And we're looking at
shift in systems function behavior
structure causing systemic
failure where the system does not
fulfill its declared goal purpose
or it becomes aberated and it fulfills
the opposing goal and then eventually
will result in systemic abuse and
aberration.
So we're going to be looking at the
mechanism how this is happening and a
little bit at the
outcomes.
Um so the the main outcome that we
should be afraid of is the existential
risk. And then of course we're going to
try to see if we can uh by raising or
increasing our awareness we
can attempt to mitigate this phenomenon.
So we have defined systemic deviation
and in particular I want to remind
although this presentation focuses on
psychology
um and cognition
ultimately its application is in the
design of autonomous
systems. Um as they become more complex
this deviation is increasingly hidden.
Uh and it's a little bit like the what
we discuss with um explanability of AI
uh black how do we make the black black
box transparent more transparent how do
we know what's going on inside the
system how do we audit auditability etc
so uh the systemic deviation applied or
uh built into hidden into autonomous
systems is relevant to complex systems
social technical systems and int
intelligence systems. So why is this
topic important? Finally, we're getting
to the central point. I think I having
illustrated what I'm talking about. I
can tell you why we're talking about it
today and why I think I appreciate
you're
listening because people are not
listening. And that's, you know, a bit
of of a worry. But why is this topic
important? Because systemic deviation is
invisible. You cannot see it at all
unless you really look hard. It's
covered. is in fact it's inconceivable.
It's
counterintuitive and it's a mechanism
that contributes to existential
risks. Existential risks resulting in
technical and social technical
malfunctions. Uh loss of confidence in
perception and judgment, mental and
physical conditions. So it actually
makes people unwell. Uh I think it can
even cause cancer in fact but I don't
have the data to back it. Lack of
awareness, loss of cognition, widespread
insanity, madness. We can see a lot of
that social economic crisis, depletion
of resources. So people the resources
are there but they're used
um not to achieve the declared purpose.
They're actually wasted so that the
purpose is not achieved and this is
like aberration screaming aberration
here depletion of resources ongoing
conflicts disagreement wars etc. So this
is uh systemic deviation is contributing
to existential risks in a number of ways
which are uh very
alarming. So when we talk about
existential risks we think of the cosmic
events like oh the asteroid is going to
hit us the black hole is going to
swallow us. This is not what I'm talking
about because this kind of existential
risks are not something we anyone can do
about climate catastrophe. We could if
we I don't know it's a bit late now
sorry but it can be mitigated or we can
attempt to avoid accelerating it if the
risks are understood talking about
global warming and all of that engineer
pandemics boweapons nuclear war and
control back. So we still could try to
figure something out here. But I'm
talking about
um something which is a bit closer to
each of us and it's the misuse of
technology. So we have
industry standards which are failing to
address the risks that is an
existential. So if the industry if the
standard body that is supposed to
identify and address the risks fails to
do that that is of the systemic
deviation and the civilization apathy.
So people are actually becoming um numb
to this
nonsense. People are learning how to
accept this the systemic relation as the
effect of life and it will contribute to
cognitive fog. I don't have the time to
go into this. Uh we'll be touching on
what we mean we mean by cognitive fog
but I'm sure you must have heard the
topic. people aren't figuring it out and
eventually possibly dementia, loss of
cognition, misinformation, mass deceit,
brainwashing, all sorts of things. So,
existential risks
uh not understanding the for me the main
the closest existential risk to each of
us is not understanding what is going on
as a result of
confounding, obuscation, confusion,
designed, confusion by design. And it
means that people cannot react or make
decisions appropriately to prevent uh
whatever escalation of
risk. So the closest level of
existential risk is information
knowledge, emotion, cognition. So is is
how we what information we receive, how
we process it, how we develop our
knowledge and how that turns or stirs
our emotions and impacts our cognition.
And then of course there's a number of
other levels here which we don't have
time to look at
but will be resulting in suffering and
harm or loss of cognition or even loss
of life. So that's existential risk is
the reason why we're talking about
systemic
mediation. In a previous slide and in
the paper these are the main categories
uh
identified. We have already seen this um
in the paper and in the previous slide.
uh and um now I'm picking out a few more
examples that have
uh where systemic deviation has become
applicable from the time the paper was
written few years ago to that which is
about 10 years almost now 9 years so but
this is a figure which uh I wasn't sure
about
but you know we said hospital you know
that you go to the hospital for for to
be cured and then you
die okay So this is actually backed by
by figures a medical yearly death that
this is only the US. I don't know I
horrified to think what if this happens
in the US I wonder how big the problem
is at global level but basically medical
error people die of medical error
misdiagnosis and adverse prescription
reaction.
uh these are three categories of uh
death called by some kind of systemic
deviation and in fact they all belong to
the category medical error misdiagnosis
adverse prescription reaction they're
all medical errors but they don't
receive attention so but when you there
are measles like few cases measles they
become like a
big news people have died of me these
big news uh and this is a type of
systemic migation there are two systemic
migations here
These figures show us that people are
dying from the health system and is
showing us that information is
representing is misrepresenting the
problem by putting a lot of attention on
the small cases and not enough on the
big causes. So in AI
uh we're looking at
the machine learning. Okay, I'm not
talking about knowledge based AI talking
about machine learning which is the
biggest uh type of AI in use at the
moment which is causing all this
interest because it's can be very
powerful but basically the systemic
deviation in machine
learning happens when data is
transformed. You know these
transformers, you must have heard
transformers, algorithms
uh and the way the data is transformed
can lead to the data become completely
different from what it was at the
beginning in more than one way. So
ultimately the AI may result in outcome
the uh process um carried out by machine
learning can be false.
When we go and look at the standard for
to ensure that AI is operating safely,
we see that the standard doesn't even
contemplate truth maintenance. Truth
maintenance is a concept in knowledge
representation, which is one of the
fields I'm working
on and I'm working on this. I'm saying
how come the standard in AI safety
doesn't mention the truth maintenance.
Well, at least this was uh now we're in
uh 1st of May, 2nd of May, and this was
true in February. So, and I have raised
the alarm. I don't know if it has been
taken. There is a chance that it has
been looked into, but they're not
attributing this to me because this is
what happened unfortunately, but I'm
hoping somebody has picked up the the
message. So, the safety standards in AI
are not uh adequately addressing the
risks.
So there is a proliferation of AICT
standards that does not address critical
concepts such as treatment and then of
course deep fakes. So here deep fake is
an interesting case because it's a case
where the software is designed to
deliberately
misrepresent the fact or the truth and
builtin. So systemic medation is
actually deep fakes is when people so
the software will will produce some
output which is fake which is not real
at all with a lot of examples and a lot
of adverse consequences and it's a type
of systemic deviation of course so in
the
moment a big drama here
so I didn't look at this
uh green deal in the Obama era for a
long time I heard that there was a
problem with the B bofu and I said
what's the problem of life fuels uh what
problem can there be with biouels and
the problem is that they are
uh entire government problem are
adopting bofules which are clearly not
right not bofuels at all like bofuel
uh the process of generating bofuel is
supposed to be environmental friendly
and creating free energy or is like non
on consuming fossil fuel by by uh in
some examples and this was designed to
happen like this. They made the bofuel
dependent on um fossil fuel because they
designed it more and then they made the
administration responsible for that when
the administration was actually probably
a victim of industry lobby that that
nominated the administration to
uh sign off
uh and accept a program which was
clearly not working because nobody in
the program had control of what was
happening and nobody had enough compet
comp to say this is wrong. Uh so it will
we we could the public could only see
that it was wrong at the end after
billions were wasted after bofuel became
a joke and after we realize that
somebody in the system is making bofuuel
fail and is making the political
administration which is trying to go
green fail and make look ridiculous
because it's they're really evil and
they can do that. They have the power to
to to do this.
Um and then uh this is other example of
um the climate change conference in
Brazil where they're cutting the trees
down to to make room for the climate
change meeting. This is I don't know if
you heard of this but this is I just
thought oh my god you know uh this is
really happening. So they have the
climate change conference and they're
taking down the forest to accommodate
for isn't this the case of systemic
deviation for me it is. It's dramatic.
And so this was an interesting
um example. I was reading the papers the
other day, the
Atlantic, and I don't have uh personal
quibbles with uh anyone, but they were
saying, you know, here the people who
are losing this ability to figure out
what's happening are not just the common
folks like you and I. they are the
people who are supposed to be in charge
of uh big
decisions. So this article was telling
of
uh you know the world's largest military
was enveloped in a level of dysfunction
that border with a conical. Now we have
the top brass who is being misled. So
think of what happened with
Iraq. One simple meeting by Powell
triggered years of war in the Middle
East war.
um uh weapons of mass destruction that
weren't there. So here we have I'm not
talking about I don't know about this
guy. I have no idea who this guy is
whether he's fit proposed or nothing but
uh what I know is that people who are
making the big decisions is supposed
these are supposed to be the most
rational best
informed decision makers who have big
power to destroy the universe uh or not
to destroy the universe and they are
confused. They're dysfunctional. They're
misled. They're taking for a ride. This
is existential
risk. And then we're looking at
psychological abuse in
general and mindbreing. Now when
somebody told me this is mindbreaking, I
couldn't figure out what we're talking
about and then and then I figured
it. When we are misinformed and when we
are given
two versions of the truth
simultaneously,
people cognition and consciousness is
become split.
And um with the script
mind is not you know we are not able to
make the best decision at all. Uh and
this psychological abuse this form of
psych this is a psychological abuse. Um
this happening
in sorry this happening in the
um organizations family schools but it's
happening at government level.
[Applause]
to somebody figures it out and says okay
I worked it out this is happening
they're taking that for a right this
system is designed wrong it's designed
to fail now when an expert will be able
will will see it they are
psychologically abused so the people uh
who identify the systemic deviation
become
harassed at
best they become psychologically abused
and harassed at best at worst they get
murdered so the systemic failures in
Boeing 747 are historical is not secret
there is there are a lot of uh reports
uh for decades there has been issues
with some safety I'm saying because it's
the large largest manufacturers but it
could be there could be there could be
others so there are systemic failures in
safety of certain systems for example
Boeing 747 and
after 747
uh came run into accidents safety caused
by safety issues repeatedly increasingly
worriedly systemically the engineers
they started shouting saying I told you
so I have reported this my report has
been uh showed under the carpet. So
people may have noticed that you know
there are safety issues or some systemic
deviation taking place at system design
level or system manufacturer in some
cases and they they're killed like this
guy died accidentally by suicide. Uh
it's a very long story but you have to
read it and it's unbelievable. Uh John
Barnett Joshua team they're now suing
but it's it's a dramatic. So when we
find out that there is something going
on and we say it as a whistleblower or
as a simple naive observer point the
finger and say this is wrong. People
become abused at best and they will
become uh murdered and uh and when the
thing is when there is enough uh at
stake and this you know there is some
lots of stuff there are some examples
um and then I'm looking at forensics I
have a paper out which I can share with
you interesting stuff but ultimately we
Forensics is sometime used to lead to
wrongful
conviction. So we are using the most
rigorous
process for factf finding to actually
produce fabricate false
uh false
evidence very
common. So why why is this happening?
Motivation for systemic deviation
systemic failure can be found in so some
of it are genuine errors. Okay, we
accept that humans are not perfect, that
systems, organizations are prone to
failure. So we okay, but it can also be
systematic. So someone has figured out
that they can
um play God by injecting systemic
deviation into a system, an
organization, a
program, a hospital, a tool, make money
out of it. Okay, which can mostly money
but it could be a number of other things
including political power or personal
power, power, money, profit. So people
are using some this the you know the
more knowledgeable people who have
figured out how to control a system.
These are the system control people.
They know how to control a system by
designing a rock.
uh and then they gain control or wealth
or other whatever from this
failure I would say. So how can it
happen? Okay. Okay. So the mechanism are
mis misrepresentation misalign and
confounding. By compounding here I don't
mean the statistical confounding factors
that you find in statistics which are
mathematical confounding data that
doesn't belong and it makes the analysis
of the data skewed. So the bias I'm
talking about the tactics to confound.
So deliberately seeding um misleading
um
decoying signals into a message. So that
it takes a lot more uh intelligence and
uh processing ability to decode the
truth to clean up the truth what's
happening really poor system design
accidental. So sometimes it's accidents
and sometimes is deliver and we need to
figure out or both. We need to learn how
to distinguish when is this happening by
accident or when is someone actually
doing it. Um the con uh so it happens
through cognitive
dissonance. So when it's injected is
because someone is
designing a response into the
individuals very often. These are the
decision
makers, the influencer, people who can
call the shots. They are deliberately
misled to have uh
dissonant
cognition. Uh and this is where a lot of
the people in power are actually
psychopaths, which is kind of very
worrying. um leading to alienation,
conflicting emotion and then of course
more general level these
conflicts in society are
um can lead to mental health issues
autism
depression disengagement people say okay
sorry I can't cope with that and we I
see you all on the beach
um systematic aberration so this is
happening day in day out everything that
we see or we do or we perceive is uh
leading or going the same way and then
we become
compounded and I suspect it can cause
mutations. I have reason to believe
that. So there is a
paper that is at least one paper there
are probably more but it's saying
mutations in human accelerated
um regions in the brain
region. Um so
mutation in humans disrupt cognition.
Okay, there's an article with
study. So, how mutation can impact
cognition and social
behavior. But what I'm looking at is the
opposite. How can the uh can cognition
and social behavior
disrupt the cause or impact mutation? I
think it can, but I don't have the data
for that. That's another possible
direction for study. So, but what we
know for a fact is that depression is
leading to health decline. Uh, chronic
stress and depressive like behaviors
associated with impairments of
neuroplasticity. People lose their
ability to think um creatively
or positively
sometimes optimistically people lose the
ability to think all
together when they are stressed or
depressed. So all of this systemic
deviation which is causing confusion,
people are losing their ability to
control their own mind, their own
cognitive process. They don't understand
what is going on. We are all at the
receiving end of someone doing something
which obviously doesn't work or is
wrong. And that's very depressing and
this is happening quite a lot. It's a
little bit what people are experiences
as cognitive fog and is something that
we should uh learn how to recognize a
bit more. still dissonant
uh consequences, dissonance,
psychological emotional dissociation,
general stress, dysfunction, reduction
of free will. We all think, we all
become conditioned to function in a way
that is reducing minimizing harm and
minimizing and maximizing reward. So
ultimately we're that's where the
conditioning is taking place. Um I have
a presentation on free will um which I
can share if people are interested and
then of course that's where people
become manipulated and unable to realize
that they are being uh misled into
something into being part of something
bigger which is definitely wrong. This
is how people
become like the you know the hoarde
behavior because not there because of
the uncertainties there is certain
safety going where everyone else is
going and individuals very few people
have uh this uh ability to
uh call out this phenomena of wrong and
um when they do their them they are risk
they become ridiculed and they become um
abused and they even murder and their
families. So it is easier to say okay
you know I've got children to think
about uh I have heard so many times
people are we want to worry about the
end of the month paying the rent and
sorry we cannot cope with this we have
to just go with the
flow so psychological and emotional
trauma so this is where I think it's
happening that uh we are mutating this
is all happening and we are mutating
possibly cause of
cancer possibly we are becoming
chimpanzees is I mean you are becoming
sheep they are becoming sheep I'm not
I'm trying to uh develop my
human discrimination
uh at some cost but uh so basically
this trauma and this
trauma are impacting evolution okay
that's important thing to remember as
existential risk so what can we view. We
can first try to figure out what's going
on, develop, raise awareness, recognize
the risk of
deviation and become paranoid in the
process and become how do you say fairly
uh petulant like you know we have to pay
attention to every little detail because
deviation can be very subtle. So you
need to be able to look at the detail
and
um try to see is this little thing going
to lead to a
bigger problem later on down the line.
Knowledge representation I'm sure I've
got more slides about that. So how can
it be mitigated? Logical integrity
important. We need to
uh be able to we need to exercise our
intellectual discrimination through
logical integrity. Whatever that is,
whatever way you define, truth
preservation, integrated systems design,
causal loops, stepping away. This is
more like a behavioral decision. When
things are wrong, we cannot understand
them. Walk, walk as fast as you can,
walk away. And sometimes we find
ourselves uh into some, you know, into
the juggle say, I had to walk away from
this. I had to walk away from that. But
eventually we will meet others who have
walked away and develop better and maybe
we have a chance
to reconsider and make an impact for the
you know future and develop better
systems obviously. So these are the
causal loops for those of you it's a
design way of somewhere here there is a
cause of the the cause for the system to
work as intended or the system to work
uh not as intended somewhere here and
here is where the systemic deviation
will hide as you can see you need to
apply a lot of attention to see where
the deviation is taking
place. So in a
previous this is coming from other
presentations and basically when when I
say knowledge presentation and it's
important I have a reason to do so I've
done a lot of work but ultimately in
order to understand what is going on so
how to maintain logical integrity we
need to be able to identify concepts to
have an idea how everything sticks
together what things are called
glosseries how
the this entities where things are uh
relate to each other in a process and we
use framing frame in AI. Uh so we have
these and how they build a process or a
function
uh algorithm and uh how these uh are
written up. So which syntax notation
language and then ultimately how these
are encoded into a system.
So we need to learn about knowledge
presentation because this is how the
system is going to by using a correct
adequate uh valid
uh transparent knowledge presentation
that's the only way to figure out how
the system is going to play
out. Then we have uh knowledge
representation as a shared mechanism to
ensure the concept conceptualization of
complexity logical and functional
integrity risk reduction. So we were
looking at our
risks and this the only way we can
ensure to reduce the risk is
by understanding and implementing
knowledge presentation correctly. for to
address the black box and the opacity
and
to improve reproducibility and
predictability. So mitigation, develop
awareness, apply intelligent reasoning,
devise better systems, develop
cautionary measures, uh sometimes non-
action. So whenever we see that whatever
we do is is uh misused or misinterpret
or um twisted um or mischaracterized or
misrepresented then it's better just to
shut the heck up and walk away which is
why many of us are ending up in some
kind of monastery situation or retreats
or isolation. we need to collect
ourselves and figure out if everything
that we do is can be used wrong because
there is a bigger evil out there then
sometimes we take this spiritual you
know I'm going to go to the beach or go
become an artist or uh or just rather
not do anything which is a lot of people
actually are taking this path and I
understand
why so but of course if we can we we
should design properly we should uh
develop ethical principles
we should
um overcome our cognitive
limitations, understand and address
systemic challenges. So this is the
system level. We need to I have a lot of
papers on
this. We need to understand the system
level and we need to do some joint
optimization.
Um and I have a paper on that which
something that happens naturally in EOS
in functioning how do you say well
balanced
uh ecosystems joint optimization is a
natural function of a health of a
healthy
ecosystem. But when this joint
optimization is prevented by the wrong
design then equilibrium self equilibrium
or selfcorrection cannot happen. they're
just discussed in a different paper. Uh
so measures again mitigation refine
design
principles strengthen protocols enhance
awareness address misuse risks of
misuse.
So the joint optimization they're
important because joint optimization
means that system should be designed to
figure itself out selfcorrect but in the
systemic deviated way
sometimes the the ability to selfimize
is
um prevented
completely. Uh this is done by
sometime by bureaucracy or rules. So
very interesting stuff and a very big
topic. So
um purpose structure behavior function
technical
system social technical system has the
human aspects like language cognition.
So you can we can design technical
systems in a deterministic way but we
cannot determine
uh how humans are going to interpret or
react or adapt. So you know we have some
knowledge representation somewhere in
between there. This again these are
slides from other talks and bias. So I
think systemic deviation is currently
seen as a form of bias where uh all of
these factors systemic
bias epistemology cognition algorithms
function representation they all come
together to to develop the
functionality. Okay. But they can also
equally be used by those very smart
folks to to develop this work. And this
is what we're seeing a lot and this is
what I'm trying to put across with the
talk today
mostly. So logical
chains. So now we're looking at we're
taking all this stuff together. We have
misalignment, misrepresentation,
cognitive dissonance, loss of cognition,
disengagement, decline, ability to take
corrective action possibly leading to
catastrophe. We are trying another way
of looking at this navigating all this
information is looking at cognitive
dissonance, psychological trauma,
genetic mutation leading to aberrations.
Possibly we are becoming monkeys, humans
becoming monkeys.
Uh seeing that quite a lot and this
uh leading to dissociation and
dysfunction. Uh some of it is visible
very clearly in the health human social
health. Poor system design uh can lead
to logical disintegration. Big alert
here. Alarm, be careful. Let's be aware
this is
happening. And this is a view of
complexity. Again, part of
another piece of work I did and we're
trying to breaking down where where is
the complexity? People are saying, "Oh,
things are becoming more complex. Are
they?" And here I was breaking down what
is complexity made of perceptual,
cognitive, representational, epistemic,
ontological, functional and systemic. So
there is this is what makes up Arabic
complexity basically and I'm uh talking
about this somewhere
else and again we I place some emphasis
on knowledge presentation and I identify
some levels of knowledge presentation
corresponding to as many levels
functionality other levels
implementation logical epistemic
conceptual. So system level knowledge
representation you can look up the
works. Um roughly consisting of
cognitive and functional areas and I
think systemic deviation is is
here but it could possibly also relate
to here. So I don't know. I'm going to
maybe redo this diagram. I don't know
where I got this tree from but the
system is could well be here. So I don't
know research agenda knowledge
presentation more for the reason that I
discussed ethical models systemic
addressing systemic challenges and a lot
to be discussed of where this is going.
So misalignment between intent and
action can be designed can be accidental
but it can be designed to trigger
failure and this is what we should be
very aware and very afraid
of
systematic misrepresentation intentional
misign
uh when designed and engineered properly
systems can be wonderful. a set
equilibrium of correction, evolution,
intelligence. We all love this. But then
when you leverage this ability to
pointed into the right
direction, huh? Then
um you know something to be obviously
recognized and avoided and they're
masked when things are masked by
misleading labels and post knowledge. So
we're saying this is so and so but
actually we're look and it ain't so at
all. And so this is where uh unless
people are paying full attention to the
phenomenon they will take the label for
good I mean to because we don't have the
ability to process unlimited amounts of
information we are tired we are busy we
are our attention is elsewhere in most
days on the children on the survival on
the paying the bills on other things
which are more rewarding and more
attract like going even you know
everything that makes us happy we are
looking paying attention to and all
these misleading labels ah you was a
headache. So to what extent can we
actually go and check everything out and
split every single hair and that's what
I'm afraid we have to uh try to do more
of so because when that happens there is
the the divergence between the label and
actually the fact doesn't when the label
doesn't correspond to what the label
describes at all that's where systemic
leadership takes place and it's used in
adversarial taxes. So it is a it is a
weapon actually
um and uh it's a weapon and the first uh
level of target for the weapon is the
people's cognition and
consciousness and so it's even
considered smart you know people say oh
yeah you know weapons can be good
because you can win uh with them but
when there is this disintegration of
consciousness then nobody wins really
and I mean a lot of people have worked
it out and
So that's where I think we should be
making the moral argument for no it's
not smart to uh make people stupid or
create
misinformation. Although there could be
some short-term gains in the long term
everybody's going to lose out. And then
of course this is
another big topic deviated intelligence.
So we are using
entire systems,
organizations, rule
sets, connections, networks to produce
intelligence which is actually designed
to mislead and dysfunction is wrong,
deeply wrong. the paper on uh forensics
which is going to come out uh shortly
with Taylor Francis uh it was chapter of
a book I have the opportunity to delve
into deviative intelligence from a
forensic forensics perspective and I'd
be happy to share the paper with anyone
interested so we're looking at evil okay
if someone was wondering or couldn't see
I couldn't see evil for a long time um I
thought everything was good you know and
now I can see it and I see If you're
asking me what is evil made of it's this
is the stuff that evil is made of. Uh
and there is probably a bit more but
this is more or less. So there is no
right or wrong but there is systemic
deviation. We have looked at the
examples
mitigation ethical considerations and uh
research directions and thank
you. Mhm. So yeah I haven't managed to
put in all the references. I'm
struggling to meet my deadline. The
deadline was let's try to get this done
by the 2nd of May. Today is the 1st of
May. Uh putting together the recording
just to
uh make sure we've got something to talk
about tomorrow. And uh I hope this thing
has been recorded. I want to thank
Michael Walker introduced me to Hector.
Hector introduced me to Daniel. And now
I think there is another guy here whose
name I don't remember who just came on
board yesterday. And I hope everyone is
going to look at this talk on YouTube on
the active inference institute and I am
also trying to do a few more slide a
couple more slides uh specifically on
the active imperence um before the
second. So thank you so much for
listening. Do get in touch. Let's talk
about this stuff. Let's talk more about
this and see what can we do.
All
right. Thank you for the
recorded presentation. Paula, are you
back? Yes, I am. Thank you so much for
listening. I'm sorry. So, what did you
do wrong about the slides not being very
visible?
I don't know. They seemed fine to me.
Oh, you seem fine because when I uh when
I looked through the YouTube channel, um
the slides were out of focus. But, uh
Jeff, did you could could you manage to
read the
slides from YouTube from the live
stream?
Yes, I was able to just fine.
Oh, that's great. For some reason, my my
YouTube wasn't showing, but thank you so
much for listening. And I have uh I
would like to perhaps suggest that we
also link the original slides or
recording to the YouTube so that anyone
having difficulties like I did, they can
watch um the original recording which
seemed to be clear enough. So, thank you
so much for listening.
Cool. Yes. Um, what do you make what do
you make of all this? What do you make
of this? Tell me.
Jeff, want to go first or I can go.
Yeah, I can start.
Um, my first thought is
about perspective and
triangulation.
Um looking
at looking at the first bit of slides
actually I took some notes here. Let's
see.
Um you know from the first from the
first point of view we have uh you
talked about
explanability and
um you know there are some tools that
are out there from a modeling
perspective that we can look at using
um like uh shap and lime for for uh
smaller or for certain data sets.
Um I think I think the conversation
about uh deep fakes uh definitely
warrants um you know expanding on. Uh,
one of my research areas is dark
patterns, which are deceptive uh, user
interface designs uh, that
people who uh, create interactive
systems uh, intentionally place in these
systems in order to take advantage of
their users uh, primarily for for
monetary profit but for other reasons as
well.
Um how about we start with that?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Do you want to
talk about it? Yeah. Yeah. Um so dark
patterns dark patterns are very very
widely used. Um they have significant
economic impact. There are FBI there's
an FBI report that came out of billions
of dollars that are lost uh and time
lost as well. So uh the dilutive effect
of people's attention being split
is
very corrupting in terms of people's
ability to engender meaning in their
lives.
And that's, you know, we we're we're
working on a a user study right now to
see how dark patterns affect the elderly
population, uh, you know, retirement age
adults. Um, I hear some clicking, some
keyboard clicking. Daniel, is that you?
No. Paula, please mute. Paulo, please
mute when you're typing.
I got some Morse code coming through.
Um yeah. So dark patterns
um
they divert your attention away
from what you could be
optimizing. And we see dark patterns all
around us. And we see deception in
nature all around us as well. And it's
not unusual. Uh deception is can often
be a feature uh in survival. Zebras have
stripes. Um you know many insects uh
use
mimicry
and deception necessarily isn't a good
or bad thing.
it's has to do with the intent and the
will of the participants in that
behavior. Um that being said, we should
absolutely optimize for well-being
um
and uh
wholesomeness and restoration wherever
we can.
Uh, another another thing that I just
took as a note here um was your
integration of optics. That is um very
interesting to
me. I've also been
considering how the evolution of
language and sight
are essential to our embodied
experience.
and how gravity curves spacetime for
example and
how sound, you know, travels at a
different speed of light and how we
evolved, you know, like as life on
Earth, we evolved um touch and then
sight or excuse me, and then and then
hearing um and then
um you you know smell and taste and then
finally uh
sight.
So that is that is I think something
where there might be a correlation that
can be explored
um from the perspective of uh control
systems and um deliberate sabotage
within a system. Uh we I just submitted
a paper actually 24 of us just submitted
a paper uh to a venue that's exploring
that um
and I believe
that there is a way forward
um and it's going to
be very conian in how
we experience erience it. Uh, but I'm
very hopeful because it's a bright
future.
Um, something else that I wrote down was
that, you know, crucibles have dual
functions and um, you know, they both
they both provide the form and the heat
and they burn off uh, the the the dross
of the in the refinement process. So
reframing some of these things as uh
more of a
um distillation
uh could provide another perspective
that uh might open up the door for
uh alternative considerations.
um systemic
aberrations. Um you know just like with
cognitive pruning we
have we have we must model and embody
and enact our
experiences so we can make optimized
choices.
Um so having you know having a system
where you're allowed to make mistakes
um or um perceived mistakes that are
really just
um life lessons uh with guard rails is
healthy.
Um what do you think Paula or or Daniel?
I I I just laid out a couple of things
there for the last 15 minutes or so.
Thank you. I I appreciate and agree and
would like to look more into everything
that you said, but I didn't understand
about the last point, the healthy guard
rails. Could you explain what you mean
there a bit more so that I understand
you properly? Absolutely. So I think
this goes in line with the uh POMDPS,
the partially observable marov decision
processes that we um use to model agents
in active
inference and when you're in a domain an
environment and oh you're clicking
again. Hey Paulo, we're getting some
more morph code. You're sending secret
signals.
Um, excuse me Daniel, where was I at?
POM DP in active inference. Oh, POM DPS
is an active inference. Yes. So, uh,
partially observable marov decision
processes.
Um, when
you situate yourself in a domain
and you have
a boundary that you're doing an
information exchange on with
um that environment, you cannot you are
not aware of the environment that that
domain is nested in. So when you have um
a a second order
connection, it can cause uh confusion if
you don't have a translation mechanism
to be able to
um exchange information with the with a
domain that you're not primarily
connected to.
Okay. But why? Okay. This is this I
understand. But um I would like to
um argue so to say
that a a user of a system who has a
second order connection with it should
be made aware of this hierarchy is a is
a matter of ethics and transparency.
So that's that is a compression problem.
um mathematically if I'm nested in a
domain that uh for example I I am a
domain of of one and um I nest myself in
a grid of uh 10 by 10 right and then I
nest myself in a grid of a million by a
million if I if I extend into that
second domain without first sol
completely solving or sol sufficiently
solving that first domain. It's going to
disorient me and I'm I'm going to be
confused and I wonder if that maybe
isn't the cause of some mental
illness is that you don't have a you
don't have a trans Oh, go ahead.
It surely is. So, I can see why you're
framing the um this challenge so to
speak. um
mathematically and but from a systems uh
uh design viewpoint that's uh it needs
to be for me the way I stand unless it's
adversarial unless it's designed to
confuse the user for whatever reason
then it should be the setup should be
declared it should be saying okay this
you're up you're here and these are the
levels you're operating in and now what
you're looking at is a level want and
that's where you are and then you see if
you don't do that you're I think abusing
psychologically the user and so this is
exactly the point that I insist on I not
necessarily expect you or others agree
depending what what kind of system
you're designing um but that I you know
I'm glad you're you're picking up on the
point exactly and that is where I think
there is a difference in the sense of
what kind of system you're designing Are
you designing an adversarial system that
you want to figure out how the user is
moving, how they are thinking? So you're
trying to learn what process going into
the user's brain by putting them into a
grid that they don't know anything about
and they have to figure it out and that
you can see how the user is moving and
how they're thinking or perceiving. But
that is absolutely um not on for for me
when I get into a system. Unless you're
telling me before beforehand I'm
experimenting I'm
testing the way your brain works then I
would say that is um psychological
abuse.
Well, I absolutely agree with you
that
the experience, the embodied
experience should be commensurate with
your
capabilities. Um, may I ask a question?
Of course. Let me just say for me it
should be commensurate to the terms of
engagement. Okay. So you to trick a user
to use a system without telling them
what the system does and how it does it
is not on. Please go ahead with your
question.
Are you currently um an instructor uh
for a class?
Yeah, sometimes I I at the moment I am
and I this is one of the things I do.
Do you use multiple choice tests?
It's not my fa not my favorite way of
testing. Not at all for a number of
reasons. But I know what you're you're
suggesting that that let me that could
be a way of testing that you know it
could be um sometimes but it's not my
favorite at all. Not my not my favorite.
How do you How do you um design your
curriculum?
It depends. Uh it depends on what the
goal of the class
is. Normally I set the intentions of
um what is this class for? What is it
trying to teach you? I'm I'm very
transparent. In fact, my tests are very
intuitive. I tell the students
beforehand what I'm going to test them
on. I said, "This is the stuff you've
got to learn. And this is the stuff I'm
going to ask you to to show me that
you've understood or learn and that
because that's because I'm you know some
people told me that I'm a little bit
vanilla and I am in that sense. Yeah, I
think that's essential. Um and I know
that you know for example those trick
questions that people ask I think
they're like designed to confuse the
student. They're really I would not I
don't like them at all.
What classes are what classes do you
normally teach?
Um mostly software engineering.
Okay. And now I'm doing I'm doing some
machine learning and algorithms.
So um would you like to give me an
example of um what an expectation is for
a student when they um complete one of
your classes?
Not now. No, I wouldn't.
Okay. Um, may I offer one as an example?
Um, of course. If I am taking a class
and uh I'm expected
to know basic commands in the Linux
shell, right? CD touch. Yeah. Uh, things
like that.
Uh would you would you expect a student
in your class uh after they finish your
class to be able to um
write them write write assembly?
It it depends who they are. If they're
not the kind of classes I teach, I would
hand them the cheat sheet and I would
say um this is these are the commands
that you're supposed to uh be using and
this is what they do and this is how
they use them. Okay. So let's let's
consider it. Are you familiar with the
OSI model or the maybe the internet
model would be easier? We can use either
or. No, but I would like you to go back
to the original question. So I, you
know, I'd like like you
to I don't understand why you're asking
me these
questions in relation to the
presentation to the deviation to the
deviation. Perhaps you could clarify
that. Well, it's
the consider this if you will.
We're talking about uh
confusion and dis and deliberately
deceptive design.
Yes.
If
I if I am a
parent, am I going to give my child who
has not yet gone through driver
education keys to a car?
I don't know, but I don't I don't know.
That depends on on on on you. Um and I I
give my 5-year-old child I give my
5-year-old child keys to a car, let them
drive.
No, but I don't understand how that
relates to the systemic
deviation issues that we've been
discussing in the presentation. I don't
understand why you're asking that
question and how does it relate to
systemic mediation?
Daniel, could you help uh maybe provide
some some of your thoughts?
Yeah, I'm hearing a a lot of uh a lot of
pieces
here
like the stated intent of a
system and then direct and indirect
consequences of the system in an
environment of of nested interacting
different cognitive
systems.
and cognitive deterioration. But
deterioration implies like some sort of
prior more
effective state. So it's not always a
simple deterioration just change in
function leading to
externalities and and risks and and all
kinds of of dangers and abuses which
were were brought up in the
presentation. So then what what I was
just hearing in this sort of
pedagogical direction is like from the
micro to the macro like the multiple
choice question or whatever you assess
what you choose to say the intent of
this course is to learn this like here's
the level or the course graining at
which the learning is is intended to
happen at. And then there's the micro on
down through the question and the way
that it's presented on the page,
ordering of the test and all that on up
through like the syllabus design and
these higher order questions. And so
that's kind of like a scenario where we
can explore systemic
deviation and think about how there's
like educational experiences. Not not
not saying this what either of you said,
but where where this all takes me is
just there's
uh a course archetype that could be
imagined where the topic is presented
and on all levels of analysis for the
students in their own context.
It doesn't deviate from
that on through educational experiences
that can be putting people back and
putting them down and leaving them in a
in a worse
situation for any number of reasons.
Thank you. Thank you, Daniel. Let me
just say that I appreciate because I
think you're contextualizing Jeff's
questions. So, so that I can understand
what he was getting at uh better. And I
must say that I haven't
um analyzed in depth how systemic
deviation applies to education and
learning, but it's something that you're
putting ideas into my head. I can look
at it. But uh to to your last point, the
consequence
is very often
um can be that um the student is put off
the subject for good. So you may have um
so I can see how it's a first it depends
on the education style. What kind of
teacher are you?
And I have had um what I consider a good
teacher is the one that leads me to the
love and the appreciation of the
subject and they do so by providing me
with the
self-confidence. Yes, it's a called how
do you say constructivist approach. You
can tell the student you can understand
this. If you don't understand it this
way, I can explain it to you another
way. And if you cannot understand it, it
doesn't matter. you can always
understand the next thing or another
thing and you can still figure out the
subject in the end. So, but there is
also teachers who will just throw you at
the deep end of the subject and let you
swim out of it. either you survive and
pass the test or where or you fail the
subject and u and that's the kind of
teachers that I don't consider good
teachers at all because I may as well
not go to that class sometime I'm not
learning anything other than survive to
the subject w without any help uh in
fact it can be a traumatic experience
and I don't know if this is uh
addressing your point Daniel but a lot
of learning experiences can be traumatic
psychologically and uh impair the
learning. I don't know if you agree or
if you have experienced that but I have.
Yeah, that speaks to these sort of first
and second order uh consequences and
also to the the disentangling and the
sort of challenges of
intentionality which is like deviation
or aberrance implies that there would be
some
nondeviated non-abberant form. So it's
like what is the true form of something?
What how does
intention what are situations when when
natural systems just are the way they
are? And so h how and then that uh that
takes on a special relevance when moving
from just the consideration of like some
sort of morphological
phenotype into cognitive phenotype and
social systems
design where the degrees of freedom and
the the
updating can be wildly fast and with
these current AI synthetic intelligence
systems etc there's the possibility
ability for systems that have
opakqueness like we've never seen and
rule updating, pattern updating that
could ex for example like accelerate
language change to to a pace and a tempo
and a mode that would be unrecognizable
or lock in language to an attractor from
some specific past and and even those
modes could be switching. So, it's like
the the control
levers are so
powerful and they can be moved very
quickly with very little
notice all presented in the case of
technology like that pretty cleanly
through a trusted
device. So, that opens up really
important considerations.
Yes. And uh to that you see
language for me it's uh must be
explicit. How do you say it must
communicate? Okay. The moment it becomes
it mutates is transformed into a new
uh formalism that only the speaker or
the system understands and the other
people because they don't have the code
or they haven't evolved the
understanding and cognition in the same
way. Um they don't understand it then it
fails. That's that's the systemic where
the systemic failures occurs like so
unless you if you're the designing if
you're speaking a language uh if you're
sending out information uh it need for a
purpose of communicating it then it
needs to be very clear and uh
unfortunately because it is
technologically so interesting to see
how it can actually happen otherwise how
can you design a system to start
speaking in its own language. It's very
interesting and it's fascinating and
it's pushing the technology boundaring
but does it still communicate the
original concept and and at some point
um nobody knows certainly uh there is no
way of verifying that and for me that is
a critical failure can that's where the
critical failure can can happen um and
where as you said we need to be careful
is that what we want or is that what we
want be guarded against.
Yeah. And and I know that you are are
continuing to explore active inference
and think about different ways it
connects. But that notion of a free
energy measure which bounds surprise
where surprise is like the information
theory converted value of the prediction
error or the deviation. So it's like
rather than training some reward
function and taking system state mapping
it to a reward function like some ranked
score and saying better or worse and
then that reward function how did you
get it is it out of date etc. Rather
than going through that intermediary
accessory ranking
system, it's possible to work directly
on the information space of the expected
behavior of the system. Like working on
body temperature and reducing surprise
about going out of your homeostatic body
temperature range rather than needing to
translate body temperature to a reward
distribution and then map back to uh
behavior choices. So it's it's
interesting to think like what are the
green light, yellow light and red light
for systemic
deviation. And you in the presentation
laid out many
many social and technical
domains where people sort
of people um bring things up and they
and at the very least they deserve to be
heard and considered.
Now I have
to as I admit that as I have in a in a
shorter video that I have very limited
understanding of uh active inference and
um free energy but as I interact with
you guys I'm kind of uh learning more
and taking the chance to read more and
listen more and so this surprise thing
you see
um
I'm don't know how many of you maybe uh
not like surprises at all. There is a
whole section of the population which
they had to create a category called
autistic and they now go around wearing
the label said hey guys I'm autistic. I
don't like surprises. Okay, that a
surprise is going to throw me off my
balance and it's going to make me reject
the whatever is being proposed because
it creates an emotional imbalance. So uh
some of us like to
um follow be able to predict or cope or
how do you say modulate our internal
responses and uh I don't understand this
thing about
mechanism surprise mechanism is it
supposed to be so in in the in the free
energy principle is surprise something
that
is is it describing something that you
think happens in everyone or is it
supposed to be good or could you want to
say a few words about this surprise
thing because surprise doesn't sound
good to me you know. Sure. Yeah, there's
a ton ton to say on this. A sort of
contextualizing historical note is a lot
of terms from psychology made their way
into statistics like belief, learning,
surprise. And now statistics is being
used to map back onto computational
cognitive science. And so we get into
this situation that's like surprise as a
general concept in the information
theoretic sense does not need to apply
to a given human's experienced or
conversational everyday sense of like
that was a surprising event. Though
that's a case of surprise when we're
talking about the information theory
quantity of
surprise. It's more about how likely or
unlikely a given observation is. And so
if somebody says like just to give an
example, I'm the kind of person who
loves being surprised and they're
they're talking about what they have for
dinner. Then at a sensory level, there's
a surprise associated with that new
dinner, but at the level of like
narrative or selfidentity, they're
confirming their identity. So it gets a
bit
specific and multi-layered when applying
concepts to human psychological
constructs. But in the general case,
okay, no, surprise has nothing to do
with the felt sense of any given person.
Okay. So but in terms of cognition, so I
this is more like a request or
suggestion. So as I look into uh active
inference and free
energy a lot of the constructs I come
across when I do the
reading they seem to be kind of given
you know and here there is a surprise
factor but they're not really explained
for me for for the people who don't have
the background I mean I don't really
understand what you're talking about
still and a number of other things which
for me are not very clearly or not
simply enough so to speak exemplified as
you're doing now with examples with the
example of the dinner. Now when you talk
about a simple example of the
dinner, it's like I don't mind being
surprised at dinner. I don't care. I'm
happy to be surprised where I there are
certain situations however where
surprise is not on um like uh so I mean
there's looking at the surprise factor I
I I am read about it in terms of
cognition. So, where does your how does
your brain respond to certain
um cognitive events and then I didn't
quite grasp where did the surprise come
in? So, uh and how and I'm afraid in the
terms of psychological abuse that
surprise is used as a tactic to
disorient that what worries me most. So
I don't know exactly how uh surprise is
fits into the whole of the active
influence uh and and free energy thing
and I haven't looked at it enough but as
I managed
to to probably hopefully summarize
enough in a few lines saying if I don't
think the brain can be um I don't think
the mind rather can be uh represented by
a model of basian brain then everything
else is a speculative is a speculation
so I mean it's interesting that you see
that way and that you can work with uh
things that I'm not particularly
understanding but maybe that's doesn't
um explain or explore the uh cognitive
um uh models that I am interested in so
I don't know whether I should be uh uh
putting too much time trying to
understand something that from what I
see is has not
not sufficiently meaningful for for for
what I'm looking at. However, if you
decide that you want to explain this
surprise in active influence for
everyone else to understand uh and then
I think you know maybe I can help you
because I am the kind of I can probably
help you make it very clear what is it
that is not clear uh so and maybe that
could help others I don't know but this
surprise thing and this energy
um uh from the materials that I've read
it's it's a a little bit like, you know,
you're throwing the the reader or the
the newcomer into the deep end of
something that they don't understand,
you know, what what's going on in in so
um uh how many people are are using
active
inference? Are there are there any are
there any expectations or projections as
to where active inference and and free
energy are going? Yeah, these are all
good questions. I don't have some
specific number but but yeah I think if
you keep exploring and there's different
kinds of perspectuses that are written
for different domains like robotics
neuroscience etc. And then there's sort
of our perspectus from an open science
and participation angle what we've done
in the space and and how people are
getting involved.
So yeah, I mean if I if you for example
had to say pala, I want you to pass an
exam in active imperence. Ukraine the
minimum entry level for active imprints
and free energy. I want to be able to
understand what it is and answer my
questions. Okay? And I don't have
unlimited resources to read everything
about it. Uh so I will have to go and
search for the main concepts and the
resources that you give me. What I think
I haven't seen yet is the cheat sheet
for active inference. And that's what I
would like to see. If you want me to
speak more intelligently about it and
and if you don't have one and if you
would think it could be useful, I'd be
happy to help devise a cheat sheet for
the instrument for energy. But I don't
know whether what I produce
would satisfy the entire universe of
this field. uh and in fact I don't
understand where is it going. So for
example from an engineering viewpoint I
would like I've seen these equations
okay the these equations and I looked at
the equations and I said okay what does
it do what problem does it solve um and
what does it do if I didn't use active
inference if I didn't use this equation
how would the outcome of the system be
different so this is what you may want
to if you want to speak to people like
me you may want to
simplify the field to answer more
pragmatic questions.
I have a question, Paula. Yeah, just
Yeah, Jeff, go for it. And just sort of
in our last closing section, go for it,
though.
When was the last time you sneezed,
Daniel? Or me? You? Yeah,
me. I I remember. I funny enough I
remember because I don't sneeze that
often and I mean I cannot remember
precisely whether it was today or
yesterday but definitely today or
yesterday I sneezed.
Do you know what made you sneeze?
So sneeze is another one of those
complex things, but I think it was a
slight exposure to uh temperature colder
temperature than the what was in the
room like a little current or
a I mean I always know why I'm sneezing.
I'm either sneezing because there is a
cold draft or because there is some uh
irritant agent in the in the that I'm
breathing in. There is one of the two.
What about you, Jeff? When did you
sneeze last?
Uh
yesterday. Um I sneeze when I when I get
when I get interesting ideas. Uh it's
called the photonic reflex. That's
extremely Yeah. Yeah. whenever I see the
sun when I or a change in in in light
temperature I sneeze. Um my point being
is that you know there's all these all
these um embodied reactions that we have
that are surprise, right? When you get
goosebumps, when you sneeze, when you
have muscle soreness, when somebody
tickles you, when you laugh, when you
cough, when you itch, when you have a
stomach ache, when you have diarrhea,
when you pass gas, right? All these
things are signals that we don't we are
not primary causal observers. They have
to be translated through a mechanism and
we have this embodied agency to be able
to
understand that there is signal even if
we can't interpret it.
Okay.
And I think that's a good place to to to
to kind of um yeah, leave it at that's I
think that's a very human
um
explanation of surprise surprisal an act
of
inference. Daniel,
thank you both for the discussion.
Allah, thanks for the the sharing of
your learnings and perspectives. I look
forward to continuing to explore systems
and deviations.
Thank you. Thank you very much for the
opportunity to share. Nice meeting you
guys. Nice to meet you.